ROHIT SUPEKAR

८ 617-909-4643 • **☑** rohit.supekar@gmail.com

Summary

I am an applied machine learning specialist with a PhD from MIT focused on research in applied mathematics, scientific machine learning, and numerical computation, applied to problems in fluid dynamics. Additionally, I have 2+ years of industry experience in the development of production-grade machine learning models tailored for business applications using large-scale datasets. I excel in deploying these models as containerized applications to the cloud using state-of-the-art engineering tools for high throughput applications.

EDUCATION

Massachusetts Institute of Technology • Cambridge, MA	06/2017 - 07/2021
Ph.D. in Mechanical Engineering • GPA: 5/5	
Advisor: Professor Jörn Dunkel, Applied Mathematics	
Thesis: Learning and investigating phenomenological models for active matter	
Massachusetts Institute of Technology • Cambridge, MA	09/2015 - 06/2017
S.M. in Mechanical Engineering • GPA: 5/5	
Thesis on experimental and theoretical modeling of oceanic internal waves	
Indian Institute of Technology, Madras • Chennai, India	08/2011 - 06/2015
B. Tech. in Mechanical Engineering • GPA: 9.4/10	,

Work Experience

The New York Times (Full-Stack) Senior Data Scientist 03/2023 – Present (Full-Stack) Data Scientist 09/2021 - 02/2023

- Model Development
 - Developed real-time machine learning models for subscription-related problems, such as serving a paywall at optimal subscription moments or personalizing messages for users to drive specific actions
 - Trained causal machine learning and reinforcement learning algorithms such as contextual bandits on massive datasets with millions of rows
 - Translated complex business problems with constraints into multi-objective optimization problems
 - Leveraged statistical estimators to build robust backtesting and counterfactural estimation capabilities for prescriptive machine learning models
- Model Deployment
 - Deployed containerized machine learning models for high throughput and low latency applications using Tensorflow-Serving, NVidia Triton Inference Server, Docker, and Kubernetes
 - Wrote performant code in Python and Go in multiple production-grade monorepos across the company
 - Built batch ETL (Extract, Transform, and Load) pipelines to construct datasets for SQL databases using Apache Airflow
 - Managed my team's infrastructure on Google Cloud Platform (GCP) via CI/CD (Continuous Integration, Continuous Deployment) pipelines and Terraform (Infrastructure as Code)
- Online Experimentation
 - Designed digital Randomized Control Trials (RCTs) to collect causally informative data for training machine learning models
 - Leveraged causal inference on observational datasets to infer the effect of paywalls on user behavior
- Impact
 - My work led to an additional hundreds of thousands of subscribers amounting to millions of dollars from subscription revenue
 - Authored technical blog posts and gave conference talks on my work on building batch models (see this NYT Open Blog and PyData 2022 Talk)

Amazon | Data Science Intern, Level 5 Seattle, WA (virtual)

06/2020 - 08/2020

- Developed a causal machine learning model using double/de-biased machine learning to estimate the impact of Amazon Advertising products for sellers from observational data
- Utilized AWS EMR (Elastic MapReduce) clusters and PySpark for processing big data and distributed model training

Massachusetts Institute of Technology | Graduate Researcher and Teaching Assistant Cambridge, MA

09/2015 - 06/2021

- Integrated physical principles in traditional machine learning algorithms for modeling active fluid dynamical systems
- Leveraged differential programming in Julia to combine neural networks with differential equations to model reaction-diffusion systems
- Modeling complex fluid dynamical systems using theoretical analysis and parallelized numerical computation
- Published 7 research papers in top-tier journals
- Assisted the teaching curriculum of two courses across five semesters and led recitations and lectures for classes with 60-120 students (average teaching rating: 6.4/7)

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming: Python, Go, Julia, MATLAB, SQL
- Tools: Docker, Kubernetes, Apache Airflow, Google Cloud Platform, Linux, Shell scripting, Git/GitHub
- Packages: Scikit-learn, Tensorflow, PyTorch, PySpark

RESEARCH INTERNSHIPS

Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution | Recipient of NSF-GFD Fellowship

06/2018 - 08/2018

Woods Hole, MA | Advisor: Professor Neil Balmforth, UBC Vancouver

• Pursued research on the topic of viscoplastic fluid dynamics using analytical and numerical tools

$\textbf{Leibniz University of Hannover} \mid \text{Recipient of DAAD-WISE Fellowship}$

06/2014 - 08/2014

Hannover, Germany | Advisor: Professor Karen Mulleners

• Performed experiments using tomographic Particle Image Velocimetry (PIV) on flow through lobed nozzles

Publications

- R. Supekar, B. Song, A. Hastewell, A. Mietke & J. Dunkel, Learning hydrodynamic equations for active matter from particle simulations and experiments, Proceedings of The National Academy of Sciences (PNAS), 120, e2206994120 (2023)
- 8. S. Boury, R. Supekar, E. C. Fine, R. Musgrave, J. B. Mickett, G. Voet, P. Odier, T. Peacock, J. A. MacKinnon, & M. H. Alford, *Observations of Double Diffusive Staircase Edges in the Arctic Ocean*, J. Geophys. Res.: Oceans, 127, e2022JC018906 (2022)
- 7. Carlos Muñoz-Royo, T. Peacock, M. H. Alford, J. A. Smith, A. L. Boyer, C. S. Kulkarni, P. Lermusiaux, P. J. Haley, C. Mirabito, D. Wang, E. E. Adams, R. Ouillon, A. Breugem, B. Decrop, T. Lanckriet, R. Supekar, A. J. Rzeznik, A. Gartman, S. Ju, Extent of impact of deep-sea nodule mining midwater plumes is influenced by sediment loading, turbulence and thresholds, Commun. Earth Environ., 2(148), 2021
- 6. C. Rackauckas, Y. Ma, J. Martinsen, C. Warner, K. Zubov, R. Supekar, D. Skinner, A. Ramadhan & A. Edelman, *Universal differential equations for scientific machine learning*, arXiv:2001.04385 (preprint, 2020)
- 5. R. Supekar, V. Heinonen, K. Burns & J. Dunkel, Linearly forced fluid flow on a rotating sphere, J. Fluid Mech., 892 (A30), 2020
- 4. R. Supekar, D. Hewitt & N. Balmforth, Translating and squirming cylinders in a viscoplastic fluid, J. Fluid Mech., 882 (A11), 2020 (featured as the cover)
- 3. R. Supekar & T. Peacock, Interference and transmission of locally forced internal waves, J. Fluid Mech., 866 (350-368), 2019
- 2. C. Kulkarni, P. Haley, P. Lermusiaux, A. Dutt, A. Gupta, C. Mirabito, D. Subramani, S. Jana, W. Ali, T. Peacock, C. Royo, A. Rzeznik, R. Supekar, Real-time sediment plume modeling in the Southern California Bight, Oceans 2018 MTS/IEEE Charleston
- R. Supekar & M. V. Panchagnula, Dynamics and stability of a fluid filled cylinder rolling on an inclined plane, arXiv:1408.6654 (preprint, 2014)

Blogs, Media Articles & Panels

- 4. <u>A. Bernard, INMA Smart Data Initiative Lead, covering a talk by R. Supekar, 3 themes emerge as media leaders share their data journey, June, 2023</u>
- 3. R. Supekar, Mentoring session on research, academia, and machine learning, Pydata NYC, November 2022
- 2. S. Goldman, covering interviews with R. Supekar and C. Wiggins, VentureBeat: How machine learning helps
 The New York Times power its paywall, August 2022
- 1. R. Supekar, How The New York Times uses machine learning to make its paywall smarter, NYT Open Blog, August 2022

Selected Conference Presentations & Seminars

11. [invited] R. Supekar, Machine learning for a smart paywall at The New York Times, Smart Data Workshop, INMA World Congress of News Media, May, 2023

- 10. [invited] R. Supekar, Causal machine learning for a smart paywall at The New York Times, Managing Disruptive Technologies course, Heinz College at Carnegie Mellon University, April, 2023
- 9. R. Supekar, Causal machine learning for a smart paywall at The New York Times, PyData NYC, November 2022
- 8. [invited] R. Supekar, Data science and algorithmic targeting at The New York Times, Analytics seminar series, MIT Sloan School of Management, May 2022
- 7. R. Supekar, B. Song, A. Hastewell, A. Mietke & J. Dunkel, Learning active hydrodynamics from particle simulations and experiments, APS March Meeting (Virtual), March 2021
- 6. R. Supekar, V. Heinonen, K. J. Burns & J. Dunkel, Linearly forced fluid flow on a rotating sphere, APS Division of Fluid Dynamics Meeting (Virtual), November 2020
- 5. R. Supekar, V. Heinonen, K. J. Burns & J. Dunkel, Linearly driven flow on a rotating sphere, Universality: Turbulence across vast scales meeting, Flatiron Institute, New York, December 2019
- 4. R. Supekar & T. Peacock, Interference of locally forced internal waves in non-uniform stratifications, APS Division of Fluid Dynamics Meeting, Denver, USA, November 2017
- 3. R. Supekar, R. Musgrave, E. C. Fine, M. Alford, J. MacKinnon, & T. Peacock, Observations of regional inhomogeneity of double-diffusive layering in the Arctic ocean, 6th Forum on Arctic Modeling and Synthesis (FAMOS) Meeting, Woods Hole, USA, October 2017 [poster],
- 2. R. Supekar & T. Peacock, Transmission of internal waves generated by a localized surface forcing, 8th International Symposium on Stratified Flows, San Diego, USA, September 2016
- 1. R. Supekar & M. V. Panchagnula, Stability of a rolling fluid filled cylinder, APS Division of Fluid Dynamics Meeting, San Francisco, USA, November 2014

Honors and Awards

• INMA Global Media Award – Second Prize for "Best Initiative to Acquire Subscribers"	
(Awarded to my project on machine learning for the paywall at The New York Times)	2023
• MathWorks Engineering Fellowship	2020
• MIT Graduate Student Council Travel Award	2020
• NSF Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Fellowship	2018
• WISE scholarship by DAAD (German Academic Exchange Service)	2014
• AICTE-INAE (Indian National Academy of Engineering) Travel Award	2014

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant, MIT

09/2017 - 05/2020

• Led and assisted teams for designing weekly problem sets, quizzes and final exams. Conducted recitations and review lectures to meet the learning objectives for undergraduate and graduate courses with 60 - 120 students.

Course	Semester	Student Rating
2.25 Advanced Fluid Mechanics	Fall 2017	6.4/7
2.003 Dynamics and Controls	Fall 2018	6.3/7
	Spring 2019	6.4/7
	Fall 2019	6.4/7
	Spring 2020	NA

Kauffman Teaching Certificate Program, MIT

05/2019 - 06/2019

• Completed 8 practice-based workshops, in which participants learn evidence-based teaching techniques

Teaching Assistant, NPTEL IIT Madras

01/2015 - 03/2015

 Prepared online teaching material, problem sets and exams for an all-India MOOC on "Engineering Mechanics" with over 6,000 enrolled students

Professional Service

• Reviewed a total of 6 articles in journals such as Physical Review Fluids, Journal of Fluid Mechanics, Physical Review Research, Physical Review E

GRADUATE RESEARCH

Physics-informed machine learning | Learning equations from biological data

01/2019 - 07/2021

- Developed a robust learning framework to infer interpretable continuum equations from particle data while incorporating the relevant physics and symmetries in the system
- Successfully applied the algorithm to learn hydrodynamic equations from microscopic simulation data of a chiral active particle model mimicking swimming cells and from microroller experiments

• Modeled reaction-diffusion systems by combining Partial Differential Equations with Neural Networks

Active turbulence forced by linear instabilities

09/2018 - 01/2020

- Extended a novel method for forcing turbulence that enables data-driven phenomenological modeling of pattern-forming systems on rotating spheres, such as planetary atmospheres
- Derived analytical solutions and performed numerical simulations using the Python package Dedalus to validate model behaviour

Motion of active and passive cylinders in viscoplastic fluids

06/2018 - 09/2019

- Derived exact analytical nonlinear solutions and compared them with numerical simulations of Bingham fluid flow around smooth and partially rough cylinders
- Developed a model for squirmers by prescribing cylinder surface velocity to understand the swimming behaviour of micro-organisms in viscoplastic fluids

LEADERSHIP EXPERIENCE

Events Officer, MIT SIAM Chapter

12/2018 - 12/2020

- Organized monthly seminars by professors and graduate students across various departments
- Planned events to promote collaboration in Applied Mathematics and Computation within and beyond MIT

Vice President, MIT Tang Hall Student Government

09/2017 - 09/2018

- Organized monthly strategy meetings and oversaw the operations affecting over 300 graduate students
- Advocated and provided input to the MIT Administration for renovations in the Tang hall building

Orientation Chair, MIT Graduate Association of Mechanical Engineers

04/2017 - 10/2017

- Planned events for incoming graduate students to expose them to the departmental social life and academics
- Managed a mentorship program to connect incoming students with mentors based on professional interests

President, MIT Sangam

04/2016 - 04/2017

- Planned and organized monthly social events as a part of the largest Indian cultural organization at MIT
- Conducted a three-day orientation program for incoming MIT students in Delhi, India
- Led a team of 40 officers and volunteers to organize the annual Indian cultural show that brings over 300 attendees from the Greater Boston Area

Hobbies

- Alpine Skiing Hiking
- Long-distance running | current personal records: marathon (3:17:51), half marathon (1:34:13), 5k (19:01)